Pranav Garg

Department of Computer Science, 201 North Goodwin Avenue, Urbana, IL 61801 1.217.377.5608 • garg11@illinois.edu • web.engr.illinois.edu/~garg11

Research Interests

Ensuring correctness, reliability, and security of software systems. My research focuses on building automatic techniques based on machine learning that significantly lessen the burden on a programmer trying to prove her program secure or correct.

Education

University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign

2015 (Expected)

Ph.D., Department of Computer Science

Thesis: Learning-based Automatic Program Verification

Advisor: Madhusudan Parthasarathy

Indian Institute of Technology Kanpur, India

2009

B.Tech., Department of Computer Science and Engineering

Research Experience

University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign

Research Assistant, Department of Computer Science

2009 - present

Verification technology that enables building verified and secure software systems with very little manual effort. Developed learning based automatic software verification including machine learning algorithms for learning inductive program invariants that scale to real software [1, 4, 5, 12] and fully automatable natural proofs [3, 7, 11], thereby significantly reducing the annotation burden on the programmer verifying such a system (partly supported by NSF grant on ExCAPE: Expeditions in Computer Augmented Program Engineering).

Microsoft Research India Bangalore, India

Research Intern Spring 2013

Designed and developed new deductive verifiers for concurrent programs. Further, developed static program analysis techniques for proving absence of security bugs, like buffer overflows, in concurrent Linux device drivers by automated learning of precise, adequate inductive invariants.

Mentor: Akash Lal

NEC Laboratories America

Princeton, NJ

Research Intern Summer 2011

Designed and developed a hybrid unit test generation technique that combines random test generation with symbolic execution to significantly improve the code coverage provided by a feedback-directed random unit testing framework [8, 15].

Mentor: Franjo Ivančić

École Polytechnique Fédérale de Lausanne (EPFL)

Lausanne. Switzerland

Undergraduate Research Intern

Summer 2008

Full-blown functional verification of a deadlock immunity system nucleus using automated theorem provers. The verified nucleus helps guarantee deadlock immunity in large Java systems with modest runtime and verification overheads.

Advisor: George Candea

Awards

Travel grant for the following conferences: MVD 2010, POPL 2011, ISCA 2011, PLDI 2013 and CAV 2014. Indian National Physics Olympiad 2005.

Gold Medal for best individual and team performance at International Young Mathematicians' Convention 2004. National Talent Search Scholarship awarded by the Government of India 2003-2008.

Publications

Journal Articles

- [1] <u>Pranav Garg</u>, Christof Löding, P. Madhusudan, and Daniel Neider. Quantified Data Automata for Linear Data Structures. A Register Automaton Model with Applications to Learning Invariants of Programs Manipulating Arrays and Lists. (Invited Paper). *Formal Methods in System Design (FMSD)*, Special Issue on Computer Aided Verification, 2014. Under Review.
- [2] Rajeev Alur, Rastislav Bodik, Eric Dallal, Dana Fisman, <u>Pranav Garg</u>, Garvit Juniwal, Hadas Kress-Gazit, P. Madhusudan, Milo M. K. Martin, Mukund Raghothaman, Shamwaditya Saha, Sanjit A. Seshia, Rishabh Singh, Armando Solar-Lezama, Emina Torlak, and Abhishek Udupa. Syntax-Guided Synthesis. (Invited Paper). *NATO Proceedings of the Maktoberdorf Summer School*, 2014. Under Review.

Conference Papers

- [3] Ankush Desai, <u>Pranav Garg</u>, and P. Madhusudan. Natural Proofs for Asynchronous Programs using Almost-Synchronous Invariants. In *Proceedings of the 28th ACM International Conference on Object Oriented Programming Systems Languages & Applications* (OOPSLA), 2014.
- [4] Pranav Garg, Christof Löding, P. Madhusudan, and Daniel Neider. ICE: A Robust Framework for Learning Invariants. In Proceedings of the 26th International Conference on Computer Aided Verification (CAV), 2014. Invited for submission to Journal of the ACM (JACM).
- [5] Pranav Garg, Christof Löding, P. Madhusudan, and Daniel Neider. Learning Universally Quantified Invariants of Linear Data Structures. In Proceedings of the 25th International Conference on Computer Aided Verification (CAV), 2013. Invited for submission to Formal Methods in System Design (FMSD).
- [6] <u>Pranav Garg</u>, P. Madhusudan and Gennaro Parlato. Quantified Data Automata on Skinny Trees: An Abstract Domain for Lists. In *Proceedings of the 20th Static Analysis Symposium* (SAS), 2013.
- [7] Xiaokang Qiu, <u>Pranav Garg</u>, Andrei Stefanescu, and P. Madhusudan. Natural Proofs for Structure, Data, and Separation. In *Proceedings of the 34th ACM SIGPLAN Conference on Programming Language Design and Implementation* (**PLDI**), 2013.
- [8] Pranav Garg, Franjo Ivancic, Gogul Balakrishnan, Naoto Maeda, and Aarti Gupta. Feedback-Directed Unit Test Generation for C/C++ using Concolic Execution. In Proceedings of the 35th International Conference on Software Engineering (ICSE), 2013.
- [9] Rishi Agarwal, <u>Pranav Garg</u>, and Josep Torrellas. Rebound: Scalable Checkpointing for Coherent Shared Memory. In *Proceedings of the 38th International Symposium on Computer Architecture* (ISCA), 2011.
- [10] Pranav Garg and P. Madhusudan. Compositionality Entails Sequentializability. In *Proceedings of the 17th International Conference on Tools and Algorithms for the Construction and Analysis of Systems* (TACAS), 2011.

Workshop Papers

[11] Ankush Desai, <u>Pranav Garg</u>, and P. Madhusudan. A New Reduction for Event-Driven Distributed Programs. In 7th International Workshop on Exploiting Concurrency Efficiently and Correctly (EC2), 2014.

Articles under Submission

- [12] <u>Pranav Garg</u>, P. Madhusudan, Daniel Neider, and Dan Roth. Learning Invariants Using Decision Trees and Implication Counterexamples. 2015. Under Submission.
- [13] Alex Gyori, <u>Pranav Garg</u>, Edgar Pek, and P. Madhusudan. Abstraction-guided Runtime Checking of Assertions on Lists. 2015. Under Submission.
- [14] Shambwaditya Saha, <u>Pranav Garg</u>, and P. Madhusudan. Alchemist: Learning Guarded Affine Functions. 2015. Under Submission.

Patents

[15] <u>Pranav Garg</u>, Franjo Ivancic, Gogul Balakrishnan, Naoto Maeda, and Aarti Gupta. Feedback-Directed Random Class Unit Test Generation Using Symbolic Execution. US Patent Number 20130091495, Issued April 11, 2013.

Software

ICE-DTREE	A static verification tool for Boogie (an intermediate verification language from Microsoft with translators from several high-level languages like C and C $\#$ into Boogie) programs. ICE-DTREE automatically verifies programs by learning inductive program invariants using custom decision tree learning algorithms [12].
ICE-Cs	A static verification tool, built on the Boogie platform from Microsoft, that uses algorithms based on constraint-solvers for learning inductive program invariants [4].
Alchemist	A SyGuS (Syntax-Guided Synthesis) solver that learns linear integer arithmetic programs. Alchemist uses computational geometry and decision tree learning algorithms to synthesize nonconvex piece-wise linear functions from logical specifications $[2]$.
P-Asi	An automatic tool for verifying P systems using a combination of natural proof tactics and invariant generation using model-checking [3, 11]. P is a domain-specific language from Microsoft for writing event-driven device-drivers. $P\text{-}Asi$ verified the responsiveness of the USB device-driver stack in Microsoft Windows phone, and is being used at Microsoft.
RANDOOP	Automatic unit test generation tool for $C/C++$ programs that combines feedback-directed random unit testing with symbolic execution to obtain improved code coverage [8, 15]. The tool was developed as part of an internship at NEC Laboratories America.
QDA-LEARN	An automatic tool that uses Angluin's L* algorithm to generate <i>likely</i> quantified invariants for programs over arrays and list structures from dynamic test runs [1, 5].
QDA-ABSINT	An abstract interpretation based prototype tool that automatically synthesizes quantified invariants for programs over arrays and lists structures, using an automata based abstract domain [6].

Talks

ICE: A Robust Learning Framework for Synthesizing Invariants	Sep 2013
Learning Universally Quantified Invariants of Linear Data Structures	
25th International Conference on Computer Aided Verification (CAV), Saint Petersburg, Russia.	Jul 2013
Quantified Data Automata on Skinny Trees: An Abstract Domain for Lists	
20th Static Analysis Symposium (SAS), Seattle, WA.	Jun 2013
Synthesizing Universally Quantified Invariants of Linear Data Structures	
Indian Institute of Science, Bangalore, India. Invited Talk.	May 2013
Rebound: Scalable Checkpointing for Coherent Shared Memory	
Illinois-Intel Parallelism Center (I2PC) Distinguished Speaker Series, University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign, IL. Invited Talk.	Sep 2011
38th International Symposium on Computer Architecture (ISCA), San Jose, CA.	Jun 2011
NEC Laboratories America, Princeton, NJ.	Jun 2011
Compositionality Entails Sequentializability	
17th International Conference on Tools and Algorithms for the Construction and Analysis of Systems (TACAS), Saarbrücken, Germany.	Mar 2011
The Midwest Verification Day (MVD), Iowa City, IA.	Sep 2010
Teaching Experience	
Teaching Assistant Software Engineering II CS428 (Undergraduate course, UIUC) Closely mentored multiple student teams on their course projects, prepared iteration deliver monitored their progress throughout the semester. Created and graded a final exam, and gardeness of the course projects are considered to the course projects.	Spring 2014 erables for them and
Teaching Assistant Software Engineering II CS428 (Undergraduate course, UIUC) Closely mentored multiple student teams on their course projects, prepared iteration deliver	Spring 2014 erables for them and ve a guest lecture on Summer 2009 ramming. The target
Teaching Assistant Software Engineering II CS428 (Undergraduate course, UIUC) Closely mentored multiple student teams on their course projects, prepared iteration delive monitored their progress throughout the semester. Created and graded a final exam, and ga Software Quality Assurance. Instructor ACA Summer School on Data Structures and Algorithms (Workshop, IITK) Designed the syllabus and gave lectures on data structures and algorithms and on C++ prograudience was engineering undergraduate students, including those from non computer-science. Service	Spring 2014 erables for them and ve a guest lecture on Summer 2009 ramming. The target
Teaching Assistant Software Engineering II CS428 (Undergraduate course, UIUC) Closely mentored multiple student teams on their course projects, prepared iteration delive monitored their progress throughout the semester. Created and graded a final exam, and ga Software Quality Assurance. Instructor ACA Summer School on Data Structures and Algorithms (Workshop, IITK) Designed the syllabus and gave lectures on data structures and algorithms and on C++ prograudience was engineering undergraduate students, including those from non computer-science.	Spring 2014 erables for them and ve a guest lecture on Summer 2009 ramming. The target ce backgrounds.
Teaching Assistant Software Engineering II CS428 (Undergraduate course, UIUC) Closely mentored multiple student teams on their course projects, prepared iteration delive monitored their progress throughout the semester. Created and graded a final exam, and gas Software Quality Assurance. Instructor ACA Summer School on Data Structures and Algorithms (Workshop, IITK) Designed the syllabus and gave lectures on data structures and algorithms and on C++ prograudience was engineering undergraduate students, including those from non computer-science Service Organization LEARN: Tutorial on Learning based methods in Design and Analysis of Systems, co-located	Spring 2014 erables for them and ve a guest lecture on Summer 2009 ramming. The target ce backgrounds. d 2015
Teaching Assistant Software Engineering II CS428 (Undergraduate course, UIUC) Closely mentored multiple student teams on their course projects, prepared iteration delive monitored their progress throughout the semester. Created and graded a final exam, and gas Software Quality Assurance. Instructor ACA Summer School on Data Structures and Algorithms (Workshop, IITK) Designed the syllabus and gave lectures on data structures and algorithms and on C++ prograudience was engineering undergraduate students, including those from non computer-science Service Organization LEARN: Tutorial on Learning based methods in Design and Analysis of Systems, co-located with Computer Aided Verification (CAV)	Spring 2014 erables for them and ve a guest lecture on Summer 2009 ramming. The target ce backgrounds. d 2015
Teaching Assistant Software Engineering II CS428 (Undergraduate course, UIUC) Closely mentored multiple student teams on their course projects, prepared iteration delive monitored their progress throughout the semester. Created and graded a final exam, and gas Software Quality Assurance. Instructor ACA Summer School on Data Structures and Algorithms (Workshop, IITK) Designed the syllabus and gave lectures on data structures and algorithms and on C++ prograudience was engineering undergraduate students, including those from non computer-science Service Organization LEARN: Tutorial on Learning based methods in Design and Analysis of Systems, co-located with Computer Aided Verification (CAV) Program Committee Membership	Spring 2014 erables for them and ve a guest lecture on Summer 2009 ramming. The target ce backgrounds. d 2015
Teaching Assistant Software Engineering II CS428 (Undergraduate course, UIUC) Closely mentored multiple student teams on their course projects, prepared iteration deliver monitored their progress throughout the semester. Created and graded a final exam, and gas Software Quality Assurance. Instructor ACA Summer School on Data Structures and Algorithms (Workshop, IITK) Designed the syllabus and gave lectures on data structures and algorithms and on C++ prograudience was engineering undergraduate students, including those from non computer-science Service Organization LEARN: Tutorial on Learning based methods in Design and Analysis of Systems, co-located with Computer Aided Verification (CAV) Program Committee Membership International Symposium on Software Testing and Analysis (ISSTA), Artifact Evaluation	Spring 2014 erables for them and ve a guest lecture on Summer 2009 ramming. The target ce backgrounds. d 2015

Tools and Algorithms for the Construction and Analysis of Systems (TACAS)	2012
Concurrency Theory (CONCUR)	2011
Departmental and University Service	
Member of the CS Graduate Academic Council, UIUC.	2014-15
Proposed and reviewed new initiatives to enhance graduate education, organize academic	
seminars, and enhance communication networks among CS graduate students.	
Student representative of the CS Graduate Admissions Committee, UIUC.	2011-12
Evaluated graduate school admission applications and made recommendations to the Ad-	

Industry Experience

Software Developer

Loop Optimizations in the Gnu C Compiler (GCC), Google Summer of Code

Summer 2009

Implemented the loop blocking/strip mining loop optimizations in the GCC compiler. The developed code is part of GCC version 4.6 and onwards.

Mentor: Sebastian Pop, Free Software Foundation

Embedded Software for Industrial Control Systems

Summer 2006

Micro-controller programming for designing a PID controller which controlled the fueling system of an IC engine, through a close loop processing of the engine speed error data.

References

missions Committee.

Franjo Ivančić

Senior Software Engineer Google Inc., 111 8th Avenue, New York, NY 10011, and Adjunct Assistant Professor

Department of Computer Science Columbia University New York, NY 10027 ivancic@google.com 609-640-1473

Sumit Gulwani

Principal Researcher Microsoft Research (Redmond Lab) One Microsoft Way, Redmond, WA 98052 sumitg@microsoft.com 425-706-7709

Madhusudan Parthasarathy

Associate Professor
Department of Computer Science
University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign
201 N. Goodwin Avenue, Urbana, IL 61801
madhu@illinois.edu
217-244-1323

Dan Roth

Professor

Department of Computer Science and The Beckman Institute University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign 201 N. Goodwin Avenue, Urbana, IL 61801 danr@illinois.edu 217-244-7068